Victoria Chess Papers
© 2008 University of Connecticut
Victoria Chess Papers.
1985-1994.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Chess, Victoria.
6 linear feet.
Victoria Chess was born 16 November 1939, in Chicago, Illinois. Chess has been awarded the Brooklyn Art Books for Children citation, the Brooklyn Museum and the Brooklyn Public Library, 1973, for Fletcher and Zenobia and American Institute of Graphic Arts Book Show Award, 1975, for Bugs.
MSS19920042
Biography
Victoria Chess was born 16 November 1939, in Chicago, Illinois, the daughter of William Leard (an engineer) and Virginia (Slade) Chess. She attended the Kokoshka School of Art, Salzburg, Austria (1957) and Boston Museum School (1957-59). Chess has been awarded the Brooklyn Art Books for Children citation, the Brooklyn Museum and the Brooklyn Public Library, 1973, for Fletcher and Zenobia and American Institute of Graphic Arts Book Show Award, 1975, for Bugs.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, sketches, original color art, text and photocopies pertaining to eleven books or stories illustrated by Victoria Chess.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Spider Kane and the Mystery at Jambo Nightcrawler's. Osborne, Mary Pope. Dodd Call No. CLC B333
Spider Kane and the Mystery under the May-apple. Osborne, Mary Pope. (hardcover and paperback) Dodd Call No. CLC B334, 335
Tommy at the Grocer's. Grossman, Bill. Dodd Call No. CLC C1890
Grim and Ghostly Goings-on. Heide, Florence Parry. Dodd Call No. CLC BC792
Bibliography
About the Author:
WRITINGS BY THE AUTHOR: (All self-illustrated; all juveniles)
(with)Edward Gorey, Fletcher and Zenobia, Hawthorn, 1967.
Alfred's Alphabet Walk, Greenwillow Books, 1979.
Poor Esme, Holiday House, 1982.
Illustrator
Mary Lystad, Millicent the Monster, Quist, 1968.
Miriam Young, The Witch Mobile, Lothrop, 1969.
Jan Wahl The Animals' Peace Day, Crown, 1970.
Will Stanton, Once Upon a Time Is Enough, Lippincott, 1970.
Edward Gorey, Fletcher and Zenobia Save the Circus, Dodd, 1971.
Stan J. Goldberg, The Adventures of Stanley Kane, Harcourt, 1973.
Miriam Young, King Basil's Birthday, F. Watts, 1973.
Benjamin Elkin, The King Who Could Not Sleep, Parents' Magazine Press, 1975.
Mary Ann Hoberman, Bugs: Poems, Viking, 1976.
Sue Alexander, Peacocks Are Very Special, Doubleday, 1976.
Norma Farber, A Ship in a Storm on the Way to Tarshish, Greenwillow Books, 1977.
Florence P. Heide and Sylvia W. Van Clief, Fables You Shouldn't Pay Any Attention To, Lippincott, 1978.
Jack Prelutsky, The Queen of Eene (poems), Greenwillow Books, 1978.
Noelle Sterne, Tyrannosaurus Wrecks: A Book of Dinosaur Riddles, Crowell, 1979.
Jane Werner Watson, Which Is the Witch?, Pantheon, 1979.
Jack Prelutsky, Rolling Harvey Down the Hill, Morrow, 1980.
Marjorie Sharmat, Taking Care of Melvin, House, 1980.
Ron Roy, The Great Frog Swap, Pantheon, 1981.
Larry Bograd, Lost in the Store, Macmillan, 1981.
David Greenberg, Slugs, Little, Brown, 1983.
“Cat and Dog” series by Elizabeth Miller and Jane Cohen; all published by F. Watts:
Cat and Dog and the Mixed-Up Week, 1980.
Cat and Dog Have a Party, 1980.
Cat and Dog Have a Contest, 1980.
Cat and Dog Raise the Roof, 1980.
Cat and Dog Take a Trip, 1980.
Cat and Dog and the ABC's, 1981.
Cat and Dog Have a Parade, 1981.
Contemporary Authors Online. Source: The Gale Group, 1999.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Children's literature, American—20th century.; Children's literature—Manuscripts.; Artwork.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Books.; Manuscripts.; Illustrations.
Occupations:
Author.; Illustrator.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials were donated to the University of Connecticut Libraries in 1992 and 1994.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Children's Books, 1985-1994
  - Ghosts!: Ghostly Tales from Folklore. Alvin Schwatrz. (Box 1)
    - HarperCollins Publishers, 1991., (53 items)
      Jacket
      Pp. 1, 4, 7-9, 11-13, 15-19, 21-29, 31-34, 36-37, 39-43, 45-54, 56/57-59, 62
      P. 61 (matted)
      Folded and gathered
  - “Ghosts, Witches, Werewolves, Monsters, and Dracula” Victoria Chess. (Box 1)
    - Cricket. October, 1986., (34 items)
      Front cover
      Pp. 2-10, 12-15, 17-23, 25-33, 51, 56
      Back cover
      Correspondence
  - Grim and Ghostly Goings-on. Florence Parry Heide. (Box 1)
    - Lothrop, Lee & Shepard, 1992., (24 items)
      Cover
      Pp. 2-10, 12-24.
  - Jim...Who Ran Away from his Nurse and was Eaten by a Lion. (Box 1)
    - Hilaire Belloc.
    - Little, Brown and Company, (25 items)
      Title page
      Jacket front
      Back of jacket and p. 1
      Pp. 3-24
      Back jacket/cover
  - “Letter from an Uncle; Reply from his Nephew” Victoria Chess. (Box 1)
    - Cricket. May, 1985., (3 items)
      Sketches
  - A Little Touch of Monster. Emily Lampert. (Box 1)
    - Joy Street Books, 1987., (34 items)
      Front of jacket
      Jacket front flap
      Pp. 2-7, 9-13, 15-32
      Pp. 8, 14 (matted)
  - No Slithers Aloud. Victoria Chess., [Note: published as Slither McCreep and his brother Joe, written by Tony Johnston] (Box 2)
    - Harcourt, Brace Jovanovich, 1992., (27 items)
      Pp. 5-29
      Manuscript materials
  - Princess Gorilla & a New Kind of Water. Verna Aardema., (27 items) (Box 2)
    Title
    Dedication
    Pp. 5, 7-9, 11-13, 15-19, 21-23, 25-32
    Dedication or back cover
  - Spider Kane and the Mystery at Jumbo Nightcrawler's. Mary Pope Osborne. (Box 2)
    - Knopf, 1993., (71 items)
      Pencil sketches (19)
      Photocopies of pencil sketches (25)
      Paste up of text
      Pp. 9, 15, 18, 21, 31, 35, 37, 39, 41, 49, 54, 60, 63, 69, 77, 79, 87, 92, 98, 106, 109, 115, 119, 127, 131, 135
  - Spider Kane and the Mystery under the May-apple. Mary Pope Osborne. (Box 2)
    - Knopf, (26 items)
      Cover vignette
      Title page (pp. 1, 127)
      Pp. 4, 9, 19, 24, 32, 39, 41, 47, 53, 56, 59, 63, 68, 77, 80, 87, 90, 98, 101, 104, 108, 115, 123.
  - Tommy at the Grocery Store. Bill Grossman., (31 items and text) (Box 2)
    Front matter A, B, C, D
    Pp. 7-32
    Text pp. 7-32